Javier Carvajal-Rojas

OrcID: 0000-0002-5312-6905

Language skills: Spanish (native), English (fluent), French (basic).

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Algebraic geometry and commutative algebra in positive and mixed characteristic. My main focus has been on Fano geometry and the geometry of Frobenius endomorphisms: Frobenius actions on Fano-type varieties and their singularities. I am generally interested in objects and concepts defined via Frobenius actions such as F-singularity theory and ordinarity.

EDUCATION University of Utah

Ph.D. in Mathematics, August 2018

Defense date: 26.04.2018 Advisor: Prof. Karl Schwede

Dissertation: Arithmetic aspects of strong F-regularity

Universidad de Costa Rica

B.S. in Mathematics, April 2013

- Graduación de Honor
- Minor in Physics

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

KU Leuven

Postdoctoral Fellow, September 2022—September 2023 Mentor: Prof. Wim Veys (Head of the Section of Algebra)

EPFL, The Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Lausanne

Collaborateur Scientifique (Postdoc), September 2018—September 2022 Mentor: Prof. Zsolt Patakfalvi (Chair of Algebraic Geometry)

Universidad de Costa Rica

Profesor interino (Lecturer), March 2013—July 2013 (One semester instructor).

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Vilpert, Singularities of determinantal pure pairs, to appear in *BUMI*. arXiv2212.01300.
- 2. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Stäbler, J. Kollár, On the local étale fundamental group of KLT threefold singularities, to appear in *Algebraic Geometry*. arXiv2004.07628.
- 3. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Stäbler, Tame fundamental groups of pure pairs and Abhyankar's lemma, *Algebra & Number Theory* **17** (2023), 309–358, doi: https://doi.org/10.2140/ant.2023.17.309.
- 4. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Stäbler, On the behavior of *F*-signatures, splitting primes, and test modules under finite covers, *Journal of Pure and Applied Algebra* **227** (2023), 107165, doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpaa.2022.107165.
- 5. J. Carvajal-Rojas, Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities, Épijournal de Géometrie Algébrique 6 (2022), 1-30, doi: https://doi.org/10.46298/epiga.2022.7532
- 6. J. Carvajal-Rojas, L. Ma, T. Polstra, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Covers of rational double points in mixed characteristic, *Journal of Singularities* **23** (2021), 127–150, doi: http://doi.org/10.5427/jsing. 2021.23h
- 7. J. Carvajal-Rojas, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Bertini Theorems for F-signature and Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity, Mathematische Zeitschrift 299 (2021), 1131–1153, doi: https://doi.org/10.1007/s00209-021-02712-y
- 8. J. Carvajal-Rojas, D. Smolkin, The uniform symbolic topology property for diagonally *F*-regular algebras, *Journal of Algebra* **548** (2020), 25–52, doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jalgebra.2019.11.017
- 9. B. Bhatt, J. Carvajal-Rojas, P. Graf, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Étale fundamental groups of strongly *F*-regular schemes, *International Mathematics Research Notices* **14** (2019), 4325–4339, rnx253, doi: https://doi.org/10.1093/imrn/rnx253
- 10. J. Carvajal-Rojas, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Fundamental groups of Fregular singularities via F-signature, Annales scientifiques de l'École Normale Supérieure (4) 51 (2018), no. 4, 993–1016, doi: https://doi.org/10.24033/asens.2370
- 11. D. Campos-Salas, J. Carvajal-Rojas, M. Villarino, On the monotonicity of the correction term in Ramanujan's factorial approximation, *The Mathematical Gazette* (539) **97** (2013), 274–275, doi: https://doi.org/10.1017/S002555720000591X

Submitted
Papers &
Preprints

- 1. J. Carvajal-Rojas, Zs. Patakfalvi, *Varieties with ample Frobenius-trace kernel*, ArXiv e-prints, 2021. arXiv2110.15035.
- 2. J. Carvajal-Rojas, T. Yasuda, On the behavior of stringy motives under Galois quasi-étale covers, ArXiv e-prints, 2021. arXiv2105.05214.

TEACHING ACTIVITIES

- Fall Instructor, Advanced Reading Course, KU Leuven 2022 Instructor, MATH-679 Group Schemes, EPFL Spring 2022 Fall 2020 Teaching Assistant, MATH-510 Modern Algebraic Geometry, EPFL Spring 2020 Teaching Assistant, MATH-105(b) Analyse avancée II, Fall 2018 Teaching Assistant, MATH-333 Chapitre choisi de géométrie: surfaces minimales, EPFL Summer 2018 Instructor, MATH 2270 Linear Algebra, University of Instructor, MATH 2270 Linear Algebra, University of Spring 2018 Utah Teaching Assistant, MATH 1210 Calculus I, University Spring 2017 2016 Fall Instructor, MATH 1210 Calculus I, University of Utah Fall 2015 **Instructor**, MATH 1090 Business Algebra, University of Utah Spring 2015 **Instructor**, MATH 1030 Intro. to Quantitative Reasoning, University of Utah Fall Teaching Assistant, MATH 1210 Calculus I, University 2014 Spring Teaching Assistant, MATH 1310 Engineering Calculus II, 2014University of Utah Fall 2013 Teaching Assistant, MATH 1310 Engineering Calculus I,
 - Master theses directed:

2013

I Ciclo

University of Utah

versidad de Costa Rica

1. Arnaud Vilpert, Singularities of determinantal pairs, Fall 2021, EPFL. (Resulted in an article arXiv2212.01300.)

Instructor, MA1004-Algebra Lineal (two sections), Uni-

- 2. Anne Fayolle, Centers of F-purity and their behavior under finite covers, Spring 2022, EPFL. (Article in preparation.)
- 3. Maxime Matthey, F-splitting numbers of Segre pure pairs, Spring 2022, EPFL.

TEACHING ACTIVITIES (CONTINUED)

Master projects supervised:

- 1. Anne Fayolle, The test ideal and other measures of singularities in positive characteristic, Fall 2020, EPFL.
- 2. Arnaud Vilpert, The Frobenius endomorphism and singularities in positive characteristic, Fall 2020, EPFL.

Bachelor projects supervised:

- 1. Emre Özavci, Local Cohomology, Spring 2022, EPFL.
- 2. Marco Cavaleri, Ring completions and the Cohen's structure theorem, Spring 2020, EPFL.

Summer in the Lab Program:

1. Emre Özavci, On the positivity of the Frobenius-trace kernel on toric and Hibi varieties, Summer 2022, EPFL.

Talks

Number Theory and Algebraic Geometry Seminar, KU January 2023 Leuven: Singularities of determinantal pairs.

Commutative Algebra Seminar, Purdue University: Cen- November 2022 ters of F-purity and finite extensions.

55 Congreso Nacional de la SMM, Universidad de October 2022 Guadalajara: $Centros\ de\ F$ -pureza $y\ extensiones\ finitas$. Recording

Commutative Algebra Seminar, University of Michigan: April 2022 F-singularities of determinantal pairs.

Algebraic Geometry Seminar, Princeton University: Varieties with ample Frobenius-trace kernel: in the search of a Frobenius-theoretic characterization of projective spaces. Recording

11-th Swiss-French workshop in Algebraic Geometry, January 2022 Charmey Switzerland: Varieties with ample Frobenius-trace kernel: in the search of a Frobenius-theoretic characterization of projective spaces.

Groups, Arithmetic & Algebraic Geometry Seminar, May 2021 EPFL: On the behavior of stringy motives under Galois quasi-étale covers.

Online Algebraic Geometry Seminar, Yale University: May 2020 On the fundamental group of KLT threefold singularities in positive characteristic.

Talks (continued)

Algebra and Representation Theory Seminar (ARTS), May 2020 University of Oklahoma: Fundamental groups of KLT singularities.

Conference "Singularities and Arithmetics," Tohoku University: Étale fundamental groups of rational KLT three-fold singularities in positive characteristic.

FACARD 2019 Workshop, Institut de Matemàtica Universitat de Barcelona: Tame fundamental groups of purely F-regular pairs.

SFB/TRR45 Kolloquium, Johannes Gutenberg- December 2018 Universität Mainz: *The USTP property and diagonal F-regularity*.

Intercity BeNeFri Seminar, Université de Neuchâtel: *The* November 2018 *USTP property and diagonal F-regularity*.

Basel-Dijon-EPFL Joint Seminar, Institut de October 2018 Mathématiques de Bourgogne-Dijon: Towards a purity-for-torsors theorem for F-regular singularities.

Groups, Arithmetic & Algebraic Geometry Seminar, October 2018 EPFL: Arithmetic aspects of strong F-regularity.

Grupo de Trabajo en Geometría y Topología, Universidad de Costa Rica: Aspectos aritméticos de la Fregularidad fuerte.

Commutative Algebra Seminar, University of Michigan: October 2017 Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities.

Algebra Seminar, Universität Osnabrück: Finite torsors October 2017 over strongly F-regular singularities.

SFB/TRR45 Colloquium, Johannes Gutenberg- September 2017 Universität Mainz: Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities.

FRAGMENT Seminar, Colorado State University: Fun- April 2017 damental groups of F-regular schemes and singularities.

Algebraic Geometry Seminar, University of Illinois at March 2017 Chicago: Fundamental groups of F-regular schemes and singularities.

Talks (continued)

Commutative Algebra Seminar, University of Utah: Fun-September 2016 damental groups of strongly F-regular singularities via F-signature.

Departmental Colloquium, Universidad de Costa Rica: June 2016 F-singularidades y grupos fundamentales locales.

Conference Posters

- 1. Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities (PDF), presented at:
 - Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, University of California at Los Angeles, October 2017.
 - Local Cohomology in Commutative Algebra and Algebraic Geometry Conference in honor of Gennady Lyubeznik's 60th birthday, University of Minnesota, August 2017.
- 2. Fundamental groups of strongly F-regular singularities via F-signature (PDF), presented at:
 - Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, Colorado State University, October 2016.
 - KUMUNU Conference, University of Kansas, October 2016.
 - Summer School and Conference in Higher Dimensional Algebraic Geometry, University of Utah, July 2016.
 - Commutative Algebra Conference in honor of Craig Huneke's 65th birthday, University of Michigan, July 2016.

Refereeing Service

Astérisque, Proceedings of the 2015 AMS Summer Institute, Nagoya Mathematical Journal, IMRN.

Prizes and fellowships

August	2012	Diploma de Excelencia Académica—awarded to the stu-
		dent with the best grades in the section.
March	2012	Beca de excelencia académica—awarded to students with
		an average above $9/10$, waives tuition for the academic
		year.
August	2011	Diploma de Excelencia Académica
March	2011	Beca de excelencia académica
March	2010	Beca de excelencia académica
March	2009	Beca de excelencia académica